Architectural Plan: The Intelligent Refrigeration Cycle ModelerThis document is the definitive architectural blueprint for transforming the diagram viewer into an intelligent, interactive modeling environment. It prioritizes a flexible data model and modular design to accommodate the 100+ case variations and complex component interactions you test in your lab, addressing all previously discussed requirements.Core Philosophy: The diagram the user builds is the data model. Every visual action directly manipulates a structured data model in DataManager. This model is the single source of truth for the entire application.Phase 1: The Foundation - The Data Model & Component SchemasThis is the most critical phase. We will establish the "brain" of the application in two new, dedicated Python files, ensuring the core logic is an extensible module.1. New File: component_schemas.py (The Component DNA)This file will define the "DNA" of every possible component. It will be a Python dictionary that acts as a schema, detailing the properties and connection ports for each component type. This makes adding new variations in the future trivial.Key Features of the Schema:properties: Defines user-editable parameters (e.g., cooling_type).ports: Defines connection points. Each port has a name, a type (in, out, sensor), a fluid state (liquid, gas, two-phase, air), and a position on the component's visual representation.zones: Defines special areas on a component that are not pipe connections but are valid drop targets for sensors (e.g., shelves, air zones).Dynamic Ports: The schema can define rules for creating ports, such as a Distributor creating outlets based on its circuit_count property.Example Schema Definitions in component_schemas.py:# In component_schemas.py
SCHEMAS = {
    "CaseShell": {
        "properties": {
            "case_length": {"type": "integer", "default": 12, "units": "ft"}
        },
        "ports": [
            {"name": "return_air_in", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "air", "position": [0, 0.5]},
            {"name": "discharge_air_out", "type": "out", "fluid_state": "air", "position": [1, 0.5]}
        ],
        "zones": [ # Defines areas for non-refrigerant components
            {"name": "shelf_1", "rect": [0.1, 0.2, 0.8, 0.1]}, # x, y, w, h in %
            {"name": "shelf_2", "rect": [0.1, 0.4, 0.8, 0.1]}
        ]
    },
    "Compressor": {
        "properties": {"type": {"type": "string", "default": "Scroll"}},
        "ports": [
            {"name": "inlet", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "gas", "position": [0, 0.5]},
            {"name": "outlet", "type": "out", "fluid_state": "gas", "position": [1, 0.5]}
        ]
    },
    "Condenser": {
        "properties": {"cooling_type": {"type": "enum", "options": ["Air-Cooled", "Water-Cooled"], "default": "Air-Cooled"}},
        "ports": [
            {"name": "inlet", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "gas", "position": [0, 0.5]},
            {"name": "outlet", "type": "out", "fluid_state": "liquid", "position": [1, 0.5]}
        ]
    },
    "Distributor": {
        "properties": {"circuit_count": {"type": "integer", "default": 1}},
        "ports": [
            {"name": "inlet", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "two-phase", "position": [0, 0.5]}
        ],
        "dynamic_ports": { # Rule for creating outlet ports
            "prefix": "outlet_",
            "count_property": "circuit_count",
            "port_details": {"type": "out", "fluid_state": "two-phase"}
        }
    },
    "TXV": {
        "properties": {},
        "ports": [
            {"name": "inlet", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "liquid", "position": [0, 0.5]},
            {"name": "outlet", "type": "out", "fluid_state": "two-phase", "position": [1, 0.5]},
            {"name": "bulb_port", "type": "sensor", "fluid_state": "none", "position": [0.5, 1]}
        ]
    },
    "SolenoidValve": {
        "properties": {"purpose": {"type": "enum", "options": ["Liquid Line", "Hot Gas Defrost", "Cool Gas Defrost"], "default": "Liquid Line"}},
        "ports": [
            {"name": "inlet", "type": "in", "fluid_state": "any", "position": [0, 0.5]},
            {"name": "outlet", "type": "out", "fluid_state": "any", "position": [1, 0.5]}
        ]
    }
}
2. Modifications to data_manager.py (The Model's Home)A new self.diagram_model attribute will be the central data structure, conforming to a strict JSON-like dictionary structure.The save_session and load_session methods will be updated to serialize and deserialize this diagramModel, replacing the old static image logic.Phase 2: The Visual Editor (The "Hands")This phase details how the DiagramWidget will be transformed into a fully interactive editor, using a new dedicated file for the visual components.1. New File: diagram_components.py (The Visual Building Blocks)This file will contain the QGraphicsItem subclasses that visually represent our components. This keeps the UI logic separate and modular.BaseComponentItem: A base class for all components. It will be responsible for:Reading its schema from component_schemas.py.Drawing itself, its label, and its connection ports.Handling movement, selection, and deletion (keyPressEvent for the Delete key).Crucially, it will dynamically create its ports based on its schema. For a DistributorItem, if the user sets circuit_count to 6, the item will automatically draw 6 outlet ports.PipeItem: A QGraphicsPathItem for drawing the connection lines. It will know which two component ports it connects. When a connected component is moved, the PipeItem will automatically update its path.2. Major Overhaul of diagram_widget.py:Component Palette (QToolBar): This will be populated dynamically by reading the available component types from component_schemas.py.Property Editor (QDockWidget): When a component is selected, this panel will inspect its schema and automatically generate the correct UI controls (e.g., a QSpinBox for circuit_count, a QComboBox for cooling_type). Changing a value here updates the diagram_model.Full Interactivity:Add: Select a tool from the palette, click on the canvas to place a component.Move: Click and drag any component. Connected pipes will follow.Delete: Select one or more items and press the Delete key.Connect (Pipes): A "Pipe" tool will allow click-and-drag from one component's port to another, with validation (e.g., out to in, gas to gas).Phase 3: The Intelligence Layer (The "Voice")This is where the application demonstrates its understanding of the system you've built.1. Smart Sensor Drop Logic (in diagram_widget.py)This is the core of the "clever" mapping. It is a deterministic, rule-based process.Component "Hotspots": Each BaseComponentItem will have defined QRectF areas for its ports and zones (e.g., inlet_port, bulb_port, shelf_1).Drag-and-Drop Workflow: User drags a sensor (e.g., "CTR TXV Bulb") from the SensorPanel and drops it.Contextual Analysis Logic:What was it dropped on? The code identifies the item as a TXVItem.Where on the item? It detects the drop was on the bulb_port hotspot.What type of measurement? It parses the sensor name. Keywords like "Bulb", "Temp", "Pressure" will be used to infer the sensor's function.Logical Conclusion: The code combines these facts: "A Temperature sensor was dropped on the Bulb Port of a TXV."Action: It automatically assigns the role in the diagram_model. role: 'TXVBulbTemp'. No second step is needed from the user.2. New File: system_analyzer.py (The System Description Engine)This new module will contain the logic for interpreting the diagram model.describe_system(model) function: This function takes the diagram_model and returns a human-readable description.Analysis Logic (A Step-by-Step Query):Count Components: It will count the number of 'Evaporator' and 'Compressor' items in the components dictionary.Trace Connections (Graph Traversal): It will start from each evaporator and traverse the pipes list backwards to see if they all lead to the same compressor.Read Properties: It will read the case_length from the model's properties and the cooling_type from the Condenser's properties.Verify Topology: It will confirm that each evaporator is preceded by a TXV, which is preceded by a distributor outlet.This detailed, schema-driven, and modular plan directly addresses all of your requirements. It creates a system that is not only "clever" enough to understand what it's looking at but is also flexible enough to model any of your 100+ case variations without requiring code changes.